---
title: Work
nav_name: Work
description: 'PCDworks has worked in many industries including: oil & gas,
              consumer goods, transportation, medical, military, and food'
order: 2
oil:
  title: "Oil & Gas"
  image: "/images/work/work-1.webp"
  works:
    - 
        title: "Subsea safety valve"
        image: "/images/work/subsea-safety-valve.webp"
        problem: "Down hole safety valves are a
                mission-critical application. Current valves
                are driven by hydraulics that threaten
                pollution when the hydraulic lines are
                ruptured. A non-hydraulic valve is needed."
        solution: "We designed and built from
scratch a linear magnetic motor to drive the
valve open and a magnetic, low power hold
open to ensure fail safe operation."
        results: "Initial feasibility study was six
months. First prototype was built within three
months after go-ahead. Full-sized prototype
took less than nine months from design to
completion."
    - 
        title: "Water cut sensor"
        image: "/images/work/water-cut-sensor.webp"
        problem: "The flow parameters of a newly
                developed ratio of water to oil detection
                method needed to be understood to
                determine measurement efficacy."
        solution: "Using sophisticated
                Computational Fluid Dynamics modeling
                software we determined our client's
                proprietary sensor would accurately measure
                the ratio of water to oil in production pipe for
                avery wide flow regimen. We then developed
                a tool that integrated the sensor into the tool
                for the downhole environment for “water cut”
                measurement. Finally, we built a complete
                flow loop simulator in two weeks, and then
                ran tests at Tulsa University to validate the
                modeling."
        results: "Initial study completed in 30 days.
                    Project completed in 6 months."
    - 
        title: "LEAP pump"
        image: "/images/work/leap-pump.webp"
        subtitle: "An elegant solution to crude extraction"
        problem: "How to cost-effectively retrieve
                    the final drops of crude from aging oil fields."
        solution: "We developed the LEAP System, a
                single artificial lift system that can be used
                for the life of the well. This linear
                electromagnetically actuated pump is
                effective with wells producing as little as a
                single barrel a day and is seen as a potential
                replacement for the nodding donkey pump.
                Compared to the millions of dollars needed to
                drill a new well, adding artificial lift
                technology is a cheaper alternative to
                maintain production from older wells."
        results: "We spent less than a year to design
                and deliver the 90Kw, LEAP tubular linear
                motor. Five months were spent in
                multi-physics modeling and another four
                months were spent building and testing this
                new, disruptive technology."
group1:
    - title: 'Water borne sensing- Autonomous Vehicles'
      image: '/images/work/work-2.webp'
      works:
        - title: "WASP Autonomous boat"
          image: "/images/work/wasp.webp"
          problem: "Real time measurement of various chemicals 
                    in bodies of water is difficult, slow yet time consuming and expensive."
          solution: "An autonomous, motorized boat that tracks inside of the body of
	water, on a pre-programmed route that can be changed by downloading new directions
from the cloud and collects chemical data in real time that is displayed on a cloud-based dashboard." 
          
    - title: 'Transportation'
      image: '/images/work/work-3.webp'
      works:
        - title: "Trinity Rail Railcar / The Connected Railcar"
          image: "/images/work/trinity.webp"
          problem: "The mantra of shipping via railroad is “ship and pray”
                because once the cargo is loaded and the railcar is placed into the
                hands of the carriers, the shipper loses control over the shipment. As a
                result, most often any damage or loss that occurred during shipment,
                cannot be attributed to the carrier."
          solution: "Taking end user requirements into account, we developed a
                suite of ruggedized sensors, some patented, that can detect impact,
                intrusion, theft, load level, possible contamination, hatch security, load
                environmental conditions, and along with location."
          results: "Shipment info is available in real time via a PCDworks
                developed gateway, to the cloud, with some local data aggregation and
                analysis. In addition, PCDworks provides DFM, and supply chain
                procurement assistance."
group2:
  - title: 'Military'
    image: '/images/work/work-5.webp'
    works:
      - title: "Automated tie-down device"
        image: "/images/work/secureload.webp"
        problem: "The Office of Naval Research needed a self-powered,
                remote-controlled tension system that would reduce cargo damage,
                decrease load and unload times, and minimize crew involvement."
        solution: "We created a system of individual units which, when
                networked together, provide the ability to simultaneously secure and
                release loads. This entailed designing a customized multi-hop wireless
                communication, advanced sensing capabilities, and a proprietary
                self-releasing hook. It also included a custom motor, high performance
                battery pack, linear actuator, printed circuit boards, and carbon fiber
                case."
        results: "Our new small, lightweight, and semi-automated system
                requires minimal human involvement to tension and release loads,
                reducing load and unload times by 20 percent. Additional uses are
                being considered for nuclear waste transport, rail shipping, and aircraft
                docking."
  - title: 'Food'
    image: '/images/work/work-6.webp'
    works:
      - title: "Marmon Food Service (On behalf of Burger King)" 
        image: "/images/work/burger-king.webp"
        problem: "A major fast-food chain is evolving to fresh product cooking
                to appeal to customers looking for a healthy alternative to heavily fried,
                fat covered burgers. The chain's equipment supplier needed a broiler
                capable of supplying fresh cooked, unfrozen product with less char, less
                fatand in less than 90 seconds."
        solution: "Our client asked us to explore alternate technology to
                atmospheric open flame burners."
        results: "We went back to our roots to a time when we were working
                on Infrared driven camping stoves. We found a new generation of
                Infrared emitting material and created burners that cooked the burgers
                iin record time with less fat and minimal charting."

medical:
  title: "Medical"
  image: "/images/work/work-4.webp"
  works:
    - 
        title: "Resuscitation Device"
        image: "/images/work/resuscitation-device.webp"
        problem: "When performing CPR on
                drowning victims and others with respiratory
                failure, it's difficult to maintain the proper
                lung inflation and rate of inflation, especially
                while alone. Providing oxygen instead of
                exhaled air is key to survival success."
        solution: "PCDworks, along with its client,
                developed the first and only automated
                rescue breathing system that works on
                adults, children, and infants. It delivers 100%
                pure oxygen in the proper flow and pressure
                regimen for each, depending on the mask
                selected. Two patents pending."
        results: "Proof of concept tests and demonstration completed within 6 months."
    - 
        title: "Infection detection, post-surgery"
        image: ""
        problem: "Can you anticipate infection in a
                sutured incision prior to the development of a
                full-blown infection beneath the surface."
        solution: "In vivo use of fiber optics in
                spectroscopy and optical notch filtering for
                detection and discrimination of bacterial
                growth in the wound."
        results: "Early intervention into a specific
                bacterial species infection in the incision
                allows for early intervention with species
                specific antibiotics rather than prophylactic
                intervention with broad spectrum antibiotics.
                Two major patents issued."
    - 
        title: "Cardiopulmonary bypass"
        image: "/images/work/cardiopulmonary-bypass.webp"
        problem: "Cardiopulmonary bypass surgery
                is a time-consuming operation. Every
                additional minute of surgery decreases a
                patient's chance of survival."
        solution: "We collaborated with an industrial
                design firm to help our client simplify the
                bypass procedure by organizing pumps and
                tubes into a compact structure. We also
                created designs, developed prototypes, and
                assisted in preparing a unit that was ready to
                manufacture. Our team further improved
                speed and patient safety by inventing a
                Vacuum Assisted Venous Return (VAVR)
                which enhances venous flow and reduced the
                size of the necessary line."
        results: "A cardiac bypass system that
                reduces the need for blood products,
                shortens surgery times, and offers greater
                fluid management options for the clinical
                team — all of which is proven to decrease
                morbidity."
---


<text-image image="/images/work/hands.webp">
<template v-slot:left>

## We specialize in
# Not specializing
<br/>

The diversity of industries we work in is one of
our greatest strengths. Our ability to
cross-pollinate information, ideas, and insights
from a wide swath of sectors leads to pioneering
outcomes. Check out these customer success
briefs to see how we found innovative solutions
to some of their toughest problems.


</template>
</text-image>

<work-hor :work="oil">
</work-hor>
<work-split-vert :works="group1">
</work-split-vert>
<work-hor :work="medical">
</work-hor>
<work-split-vert :works="group2">
</work-split-vert>